Guide to the Earl J. Hamilton Papers, 1350-1995 and undated (bulk 1650-1940) RL.00496
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research Papers Series, [ca. 1592]-1969 and undated
  - Research on John Law:
    - Various notes on Law and the financial system in early 1700s, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Various notes on Law and finance: article on Law, 1957, May 4, and clippings, undated (Box 14)
    - Prices and Wages in Southern France Under John Law's System, 1937, Feb. (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous - typescripts, pamphlets, and notes, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Notes: Prices, Wages, and Industrial Revolution, 1500-1700, undated, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Galliani Economista, 1949 (Box 14)
  - Various typescripts, articles, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Bourbon Reform, typescript and handwritten notes, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Role of War in Modern Inflation, notes, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Wages in Valencia, [ca. 1600-1630] (Box 14)
  - Het Molenpanorama and Primer Congreso de Historia de Andalucia, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Mercurius, 1720 (Box 14)
  - Distribution of Earnings, 1780 (see folder 5 of this box) (Box 14)
  - Notes and transcriptions, various dates and n.d (Box 14)
  - Complete edited copy of Price History and bibliography, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - The History of Prices Before 1750, undated (Box 14)
  - The Spice Trade, various dates and undated (Box 14)
  - Bubas [Plagues], undated (Box 14)
  - Archivo de Ministerios Bogotá Transcriptions of documents from the Ministerio de Relaciones Exteriores, Archivo Diplomático, Colombia, typescripts, [ca. 1800-1820] and undated (Box 15)
  - Archivo Historico Nacional Bogotá Transcriptions of various documents on regulation of trade and manufacturing in South America; wars of independence; role of Fernando VII, typescripts, [ca. 1800-1820] and undated (Box 15)
  - Papers, notes, footnotes on mercantilism, various dates and undated (Box 15)
  - Various notes and figures on Spanish mercantilism, [1780s] and undated (Box 15)
  - Transcriptions especially dealing with mercantilism (AGN Mexico 1592-1710) and Russians in California, typescript (Box 15)
  - Economic Background of the Monroe Doctrine, typescripts of lecture delivered at Yale, undated (Box 15)
  - Economic Origins of the Monroe Doctrine, undated (Box 15)
  - Spanish mercantilism, various dates and undated (Box 15)
  - Merchants and agents in London and Amsterdam, typescript, 1718-1719 (Box 15)
  - Lectures in Santander, 1933 (Box 15)
  - Prices and Progress, typescripts, 1952, Fall, other dates and undated (Box 15)
  - Averiguación de los que quebraron tomas, metates, 1799, typed transcript (Box 15)
  - Research papers on agriculture; wages in England; diseases in Indies; other topics dealing with Spain; inflation; hemp in Peru, various dates and undated (Box 15)
  - Reglamento para flotas, typed transcriptions; cedulas on "Lino y canamo" [hemp plants], 1773 (Box 15)
  - Mr. Trevenen's Plan to establish trade on the Northwest Coast of America, photostat of document [in French, with glass in English], from original in Library of Congress, 1757 (Box 15)
  - Notes on Prices, [1500s-1600s] and undated (Box 15)
  - Notes on Vales Retired (Box 15)
  - Very poor Xerox reprint of article on Valentin de Foronda, early 19th century, Revista de Economia Política, 1959 (Box 15)
  - Photostats of documents on fabricas, gremias, [1770s]-[1780s] (Box 15)
  - Bound volumes of photostats from French archives dealing with French finance and John Law: (Box 16)
    - Arrets sur le systéme de Jean Law, 1722-1733 (Box 16)
    - Memoires sur les finances systéme de Jean Law, vol. 1, undated (Box 16)
    - Memoires sur les finances systéme de Jean Law, vol. 2, undated (Box 16)
    - Lettres des intendants sur le systéme de Jean Law,, 1709-1720 (Box 16)
    - Liquidation du systéme de Jean Law, vol. 1, 1740 (Box 16)
    - Liquidation du systéme de Jean Law, vol. 2, 1725 and undated (Box 16)
- Original Documents Series, 1584-1829 (bulk 1700-1830s)
  Hundreds of original documents in Spanish and French, primarily from the 18th and 19th centuries but also including some 16th and 17th century materials. Chiefly consist of royal Spanish cedulas outlining Crown economic policy and concern over investments; plans to establish the Bank of Spain; expropriation of Jesuit lands; trade regulation; control of vagabonds; and sumptuary rules for dress. The documents from the 1800s chronicle the French occupation of Spain and the restoration of Fernando VII; the proclamations in the oversize folder (see the Oversize Series) include public declarations about resistance to Napoleon. Arranged in original order.
  - 1584-1829 (Box 17)
  - 1596-1806 (Box 18)
- Research Notecards Series, [ca. 1920s-1980s] and undated
  Undated notecards containing background research notes and transcriptions of original sources for Hamilton's investigations on John Law, the Spanish economy, the Monroe Doctrine, mercantilism, and various other topics. An outline of chapters in Hamilton's personal papers suggests he intended to write a book on this subject, in addition to the articles he published. The cards about John Law have been interfiled with subject headings to ease use by researchers.
  - Notecards, unsorted (Box 19-27)
    Notes on shipping manifests for imports of valuables, 1760s-1790s; reports on treasure, prices, wages, and Spanish monetary policy; lecture notes, including general economics of the 20th century; mercantilism, particularly Spanish mercantilism; the Moors; Bank of Spain and Banco de San Carlos notes; and many other topics. These notecards are unsorted and unprocessed.
  - Notecards on John Law, 17th-18th century (Box 31-51)
    Though these notecards remain unprocessed, index cards relating to John Law have been interfiled with headings and subjects by an external researcher.
- Additional Unarranged Papers Series, 1390-1985 and undated (bulk 1929-1949)
  Drafts of papers, notes, and other research materials not directly related to Hamilton's research for major works. Arranged in original order as received. Dates given below in descriptions of primary source materials reflect the dates of the original items, and not the date on which the modern transcript or photocopy was made.
  - Research papers ("Precious Metals," "El Banco Nacional de San Carlos," "Las consecuencias económicas de la expulsion de los moriscos"), various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - American Treasure and the Rise of Capitalism, 1500-1700, 1929, Nov. (Box 28)
  - English Prices and Public Finance, 1660-1822, Elizabeth Boody Schumpeter, 1938 (Box 28)
  - Notes on Dissertation de peste, various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - Monetary Disorder and Economic Decadence in Spain, 1651-1700, 1943, Dec. (Box 28)
  - Growth of Rigidity in Business During the Eighteenth Century, 1940, Mar. (Box 28)
  - Origin and Growth of the National Debt in Western Europe, 1947, May, various dates (Box 28)
  - Origin and Growth of the National Debt in France and England, 1949, various dates (Box 28)
  - Edwin Francis Gay, [1867-1946], 1947, June (Box 28)
  - Imports of American Gold and Silver into Spain, 1503-1660, 1929, May (Box 28)
  - Money and Economic Recovery in Spain Under the First Bourbon, 1701-1746, 1943, Sept. (Box 28)
  - Wages and Subsistence on Spanish Treasure Ships, 1503-1660, 1929, Aug. (Box 28)
  - La monnaie en Castille, 1501-1650, 1932, Mar.-May (Box 28)
  - VIII, The Decline of Spain, 1938, May, various dates (Box 28)
  - Use and Misuse of Price History, 1944, Dec., various dates (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous financial notes from various archives (Spanish and Dutch), various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous financial notes from archives (Dutch interest rates, 1729-1790) (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous financial notes from archives (more interest rates; 1632-1640, 1801-1811, 1791-1800, 1611-1620) (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous financial notes from archives (interest rates); Haarlem 1635-43, 1645-50; Amsterdam 1650-90 (Box 28)
  - Amsterdam interest rates 1691-1710, 1621-1630 (Box 28)
  - Various notes, research, drafts for unclassified papers, various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - Research notes, drafts, etc., various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - Unidentified research notes on the 18th century, undated (Box 28)
  - Livres Anciens et Modernes, #53 and 65, various dates and undated (Box 28)
  - Livres Provenant de la Bibliotheque, 1984, Mar. 22, various dates (Box 28)
  - The Case for Communism, 1932 (Box 28)
  - Bibliothéque Nationale: manuscript request forms, 1960 (Box 28)
  - Unclassified ledger sheet, undated (Box 28)
  - The Sources of Sir Nicholas on English Baron Society Collection, 1250-1700, undated (Box 28)
  - Guggenheim report, 1985 (Box 28)
  - Photographs:
    - Home Folks, Uncle Ed, Eva's Family, undated (Box 28)
    - Photos from the Archivio di Stato, Genova (Italy), undated (Box 28)
    - Photo of a page from an account book, 1390, Feb. 20 (Box 28)
  - Empty postal bag for microfilm, undated (Box 28)
  - Information for the Banco Nacional de San Carlos, 1784-1829 (Box 28)
- Microfilms Series, 1783-1884 and undated
  Various films, including negative strips and microfilm reels, related to Hamilton's research on the French and Spanish economies and various other subjects. In original order with titles, often obscure, transcribed from items.
  Most dates given below in item descriptions refer to the dates of original historical documents and not to the date on which film was created.
  - Observations d'un banquier de la Banque d'Espagne, undated (Box 30)
  - Boletin oficial Ministerio Hacienda, 1850; Banco de San Fernando (microfilm) (Box 30)
  - Memoria historica, mayores de Madrid, (microfilm), 1884 (Box 30)
  - Archivo General de la Nación Mexico -- Cuarta Junta General, 1783, and several cedulas reales (microfilm) (Box 30)
  - Earl J. Hamilton, Banco de España, "Archivo" (film), undated (Box 30)
  - Earl J. Hamilton, unidentified film and negatives, undated (Box 30)
  - Documentos del Archivo del Conde de Colrerras; No. 168 (Leg 3-28); No. 164 (Leg 3-24), undated (Box 30)
  - Microfilm of unidentified original documents, undated (Box 30)
  - Banco de San Carlos, 20th Junta to Junta of 1813 (Box 30)
  - Original documents from Spain received in 1949, undated (Box 30)
- Oversize Materials Series, 1765-1836 and undated
  - Archivio di Stato di Torino (photocopies), undated (Box 29)
  - Primary materials on John Law (photocopies), undated (Box 29)
  - Amsterdam broadsides, 1795-1796 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Spanish proclamations (cedulas reales), 1765-1836 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - 18th century French printed materials (5 items) (Oversize-folder 3)